we're in the middle of a new phase in
the culture war that first started in
the 1960s but instead of left against
right now each side has fragmented into
different tribes fighting amongst
themselves a multipolar war
welcome to culture war 2.0 to navigate
it we need new tools
baccala so I think people have an idea
of what the culture is is is people
battling over ideas mainly in the
political landscape and in our
whitepaper we invited the reader to view
culture war 1.0 as what was occurring in
the 90s something between the secular
left versus the religious right and some
of the battle fronts there were you know
gay marriage women's issues of abortion
and largely which we'll get to the
moment is that cultural or 1.0 the
second I left one it essentially and
this opened the door for culture war 2.0
so I think to understand that transition
it's important to review this idea a
mental model from international
relations called polarity
there's three types of polarities
there's uni polarity there's by polarity
and there's multipolarity unipolarity is
one country essentially dominating so
Pax Britannica or Pax Americana by
polarity is the Cold War when there's
two superpowers sort of keeping each
other in check the US and the USSR and
multipolarity is when there's multiple
countries that were maybe equally
powerful and you're there's a lot of
uncertainty in these situations and
usually these are the most chaotic
moments in our history so just before
World War one or before World War two it
was said to be a multipolar state so we
use this polarity idea with the culture
war culture war 2.0 was a multipolar
affair where there's not just two ideas
two positions in logical space competing
with each other it was a multitude of
different ideologies combatting
so all these different viewpoints are
what we dubbed medic tribes it's sort of
like capture the flag but it's its
capture the meta-narrative the the
narrative that can help all these
different narratives so the term that we
like to use was the the noosphere
essentially just a collective
consciousness so it seems like a race
between capturing this meta-narrative I
have a sort of a proclivity to engage in
all sorts of ideas from all all the
spectrums the political spectrum of the
philosophical spectrums a theological
ones so I created a group called
intellectual Explorers Club so the idea
is that were performative agnostics
where we can act as if an idea is true
without accepting it as true it was
something interesting about the frame of
the group the intellectual Explorers
Club because it attracted invited all
sorts of different people with different
ideologies from feminists to men's
rights activists to conservatives
liberals and I was the facilitator
taking in all these points of views and
just feeling the tension of people
waiting for their turn so they can spit
out their position and I think this
afforded me understanding and I got a
visceral level of the culture war
because I got a front-row seat to it to
speak personally I felt the existential
loneliness just sort of being in my
intellectual circles having a
conversation because there's a sense
that people are so eagerly attached to
their ideas that they were just waiting
for you to finish talking so they can
kind of you know impose their worldview
on you and there's a lack of care in all
fronts from all all spectrums and I
found the act of understanding someone's
worldview what they believed to be true
sort of like an act of love it disarmed
them in a way and it disarmed me too
because then invited me into their world
and it was unexpected the insights that
I got from it and the metaphor I liked
is the blind men in the elephants where
there's all these blind men they're
touching an elephant and they view their
point on the elephant where they're
touching it at the trunk or or the tail
as their reality and what the good thing
about that is
that they're hyper focused on that area
they feel the texture they can smell it
and that affords them ability to see
things that we might not otherwise see
if we weren't touching that spot but the
problem is is that if you just view that
spot as the entirety of reality then
you're in trouble you need to talk to
each other so the way I see the cultural
right now is all these blind men just
yelling at each other
you know violently and my hope my kind
of this idea of being a performative
agnostic is if people to invite them in
a space of playful uncertainty the
sexxxy uncertainty if you will so they
can get to talk to each other and figure
out their world so mimetic tribes you're
probably familiar with some of the names
that are active in the culture war
whether it be the social justice
activists black life matters me too
alt right man Oh sphere we can even say
the new atheist or rationalist post
rationalists Street epistemology any
sort of worldview that's sort of
defining what culture is and sort of
imposing their view on it and we created
the spreadsheet where we had a taxonomy
whose meta taxonomy that had Telos
they're their main purpose
what would stir if their goal
existential threat what are they most
worried about mental models how they how
they view the world their sacred values
what do they view most important that if
you transgress it you'll trigger them
and I think you know a trigger warning
applies to all mimetic tribes all sort
of worldviews and the idea is that these
nomadic tribes are all combating with
each other and all these odd alliances
are forming there's a the class-based
Left is fighting against the the social
justice left reactionary right is is
fighting against the more traditional
conservative the alt-right versus the
old left there's no kind of clear
grounds anymore and this is creating a I
think sense of anxiety because we don't
know what we're gonna say what and if we
say something and might trigger a
certain tribe that we don't want to be
triggered
I do think there's intertribal
competition amongst what was
traditionally known as the left and then
the right like i like i mentioned the
class base left versus the social
justice left this idea of cancel culture
or what mark fisher calls the vampyre
castle people on the left just as well
as people on the right could get
cancelled these days and same thing with
the the right there's a whole thing
don't punch right but a lot of people
are punching right and left these days
and so there's a sense that you know you
don't know what will defend what people
or what will trigger what tribe the idea
was an invitation to the reader to look
at it from a different perspective and I
view this this this whole whole white
paper in mimetic tribes in the frame
that this is a multipolar almost
postmodern war is this sort of a
psychoactive drug because if you see the
the mimetic tribe that you belong to
alongside all these other mimetic tribes
that might jog you out of your belief
system just for a moment
one aspect about mimetic tribes is this
the sense that they're disembodied
because they're exercising this sense of
tribalism around a certain idea a
certain ideology a certain mean Plex but
not really meeting or go hearing in
person and there's a an egoic aspect to
this there there's their ego likely
attached to the ideas that there are
fighting with where I think what rebel
wisdom is gesturing towards and various
different people in a sense making web
is trying to create an embodied tribe
where people actually get together in
person and explore ideas
so we had four events that brought us to
where we are today in culture war 2.0
event one was surprisingly the fall of
Occupy there was an energy in the air
when Occupy was going on a revolutionary
spirit with the left was a class-based
left and when Occupy fell there was a
period of leftist activism on the left
that went quite quiet in the mainstream
from around 2011 to 2015 and during this
time the left at least publicly pivoted
towards more of a social justice ideas
more more of what they call woke and was
interesting to notice during this time
period because it seemed like social
justice was in the air
it was just amplifying and corporations
co-opted the social justice means
specifically HR departments and PR
departments and we have this kind of
provocative line is that corporations
can be woke but they can't be anti
capital so this essentially neutered the
left for a time period the the
class-based left and it sort of
amplified the social justice narrative
in society at large
so the second event was oberfeld vs.
Hodges when the Supreme Court in America
legalized gay marriage across the
country and as Rod Dreher said this was
the death blow to the religious right
this was the end of the culture war as
he put it or culture war 1.0 as we
framed it and this was sort of the
beginning of culture war 2.0 so event 3
we provocatively said was Caitlyn Jenner
and I recall hearing something from Joe
Rogan or what I believe I heard from Joe
Rogan and he essentially said that the
reason why Trump won was because Caitlyn
Jenner you know right when the gay
marriage legislation was passed the
trans issue just rushed into the public
public mind and a lot of people might
have not been ready for this the slew of
trans issues started arising bathroom
bills trans athletes and pronouns and a
lot of famous figures in the culture war
came on the scene due to these issues a
lot of the figures in the intellectual
dark rub for example like ben shapiro
and our Toronto's own jordan Peterson
came out specifically for the pronoun
issue
event for the Kaos President Donald
Trump and there there's something in the
air when Trump was running it just felt
like chaos something we were seeing
something that hasn't happened before
and there's a quote by Trump Tuesday's
he loves chaos and maybe it's a part of
his negotiation strategy of how he makes
people puts people in a state of
uncertainty and he's bringing his
business techniques and his negotiation
techniques into the political arena and
during this time - there's weird
occurrences with Pepe the Frog the chaos
God and there's just the sense that
something was going on that was
stabilizing - where everyone
so we talked about six crises and four
events that led to culture war 2.0 and I
think it's useful to have these in mind
because they offer sort of a historical
and then philosophical events that
occurred that sort of give understanding
of where we are today so the first one
that we we talked about was
secularization and the meaning crisis
and how I hold the meaning crisis or one
way that I hold it is there's this lack
of meta-narrative or grand narrative
that sort of justifies an ecology of
practices that can engender and sustain
that felt sense of meaningfulness and we
don't have that anymore
we reference the the famous Nietzsche in
line God is dead and the idea that once
that Christian met a narrative got
destroyed in society there was no
justification for doing a lot of things
that might engender that state of
meaningfulness and a lot of secular
theorists that they have this term
called the substraction theory of
secularization and the idea that once
you remove religion from our formal
institutions will become all rational
and scientific but as the famous
Canadian philosopher Charles Taylor
points out that's not the case we won't
be evolving around the new meta
narrative of science and rationality
were more likely to evolve into a state
of plurality where all these different
viewpoints are wrestling with each other
the next crisis is the reality crisis
and the greedy --nt associated with that
is fragmentation and I like Scott Adams
analogy of the the two movie screens in
the culture war so you're looking at the
same reality like let's say something
about Trump's impeachment and CNN is
raging against Trump he sees he's
literally Hitler and then Fox News is
viewing Trump as some sort of Savior and
Scott item's invites everyone to have
this - movie screen idea to look at
reality through these lenses but we
suggest in our white paper is that it's
not just two movie screens it's a
Netflix variety level
of reality tunnels coming at us and if
we're sensitive to all the ones that are
active then we might get a better sense
of how to navigate this space and that
French postmodern philosopher Leo Tarr
he calls the postmodern condition not
one of relativism but one of
fragmentation and that is the sense that
were in a situation where all these
different metaphysics and epistemology
are actively trying to impose themselves
and sense make but without communicating
with each other
atomization and the belonging crisis I
like the the notion of Martin boobers
ayat verses I though relating and I
think we're in a situation where and you
can kind of like plopping your
capitalism critique that were in a it
relating environment and see right mills
he has a wonderful term called the
marketing mentality it's not only am i
treating you as an instrument to use to
get to something I'm also making myself
an instrument to be used so you can get
to something and this is sort of a sense
of bullshit's in the air people are not
relating for its own sake they are
relating in order to the profit motive
or means to an end and I think this is a
sense of deep deep loneliness that's
associated with this and so people are
running towards things maybe they
shouldn't be running towards such as
mimetic tribes so individuals are
instrumentalizing each other the I it in
Buber terms is I'm treating you as an
object to get something from you and not
treating you as a human being that I can
relate with it's a globalization in the
proximity crisis all these tech
utopianist s-- they thought that the
Internet or Facebook or social media was
going to be a panacea they're gonna
connect everyone but that has not been
the case and another Canadian
philosopher Toronto's own Marshall
McLuhan he predicted the situation he
called it the global village and he
viewed it as a point where disagreements
will occur on all fronts he did not have
a naive view of the situation
philosopher Byung chul Han he says that
distance creates respect but when you
don't have that distance from someone or
their viewpoints when you know too much
about them then a spectacle emerges then
battles occur and this is a kind of
verified by modern psychologists when
they have these terms called
dissimilarity Cascades the more you
actually know about someone the more you
dislike them and environmental spoiling
once the environment you don't like
someone in an environment it corrupts
the whole the whole ecosystem and so you
know the whole saying good fences make
good neighbors we tore down our fences
we can peer inside someone's world view
someone's philosophy and it's triggering
especially if it transgresses our sacred
values and I love this saying in my more
naive days you know if you know
someone's complete story you can't help
but love them that might be true but
maybe the step before that is you have
to hate them it's a stimulation in the
sobriety crisis we're living in a state
of what they call a supernormal stimuli
that do to the profit motive or whatever
there's certain stimuli that are just so
extreme so exaggerated that it triggers
our evolutionary response porn
pornography is a example of this laugh
tracks junk food sugar whatever and
social media is a prime example of this
the likes you know we're hunting for the
likes and we have been addicted to these
platforms in very subtle ways too we
referenced this study on the jewel
beetle so in Australia there is this
jewel beetle that almost went extinct
and the reason why is because there is
these beer studies that people started
throwing and then they're kind of
ecosystem and they kind of looked like a
female's but right and the male's they
started having attempted impacting
intercourse with these beer studies and
they were dying off because they it was
just it was so exaggerated the beer
stubby that they were trying to make
love with it
and they just were starving to death
they were being attacked by ants and so
the population almost went extinct and
then once they started removing these
beer studies then they started coming
back and we use that as a metaphor for
our current situation so the
weaponization in the warfare crisis we
start the section off by talking about
Alexander Dubin which some people refer
to as Putin's brain or the most
dangerous philosopher in the world and
he wrote a book in the late 90s sort of
outlining some of the stuff that Russia
is doing today about sowing discord in
America in America's internal politics
and the strategy there was to fund and
support radical groups within America
that make them fight each other and by
following the 2016 election and the
Russian sock puppet army they did this
strategy they they did they fund Bernie
Sanders the the Green Party Trump they
even Trump even funded a pro and anti
Trump rally at the same time just to
create what some people call chaos
operations create chaos for its own sake
and it's just not Russia doing this it's
other countries corporations lone wolf
hackers mimetic mercenaries like
Cambridge analytic everyone is trying to
weaponize our mind right now and we're
in a vulnerable state because we're
addicted to these platforms referencing
back to the sobriety crisis
we're being weaponized for reasons we're
not even aware of how do we mediate
amongst all these warring tribes and I
view mimetic mediation as the hard
problem of culture war 2.0 in
referencing the blind man and the
elephant how do we get all these blind
men to talk to each other so the
exciting thing that I find about mimetic
mediation is it's an open conversation
it's an open discussion on what exactly
it is what mindset is needed in order to
adopt it and what kind of techniques and
tools can we use to go about it and I
have some ideas that I'm playing with
and I invite the listener right now to
kind of
and join in on this conversation but
there's things that we're experimenting
with in Toronto called the anti debate
where it's sort of a gamification of
understanding there there's
conversational modalities like empathy
circles where they apply Carl Rogers act
of listening to a four-way conversation
getting people to look at new sites met
a new sites like all sides that kind of
shows the bias of each news platform on
one issue or letter dot wiki inviting
intellectuals that might not have spoke
to each other otherwise to get them to
have a long-form good faith conversation
so the matrix introduced this concept of
the blue pill versus red pill and this
was co-opted by more of a reactionary
tries but going back to its original
meaning the blue pill is what you're
born into it's nobody really takes the
blue pill and you're given the blue pill
and you're not aware that you're taking
the blue pill
so it's unexamined consensus reality and
the red pill is the dark truths that you
have not yet explored it's it's the
views that sort of rip your current or
previous reality underneath your feet
and taking the red pill has a tendency
to try belies us make us angry give us
sort of a purpose to fight for something
where there's another pill that
Venkatesh Rao calls the gray pill and
this is a pill that sort of muddies the
water of your previous red pill truths
it adds a little bit uncertainty to your
positions and at first this might be
anxiety producing this might engender an
existential crisis but if you stay with
it long enough if you stay with that
that gray pill sense life starts
becoming playful you can start playing
with ideas there's a sexy uncertainty
starts emerging and taking the gray pill
is reintroducing nuance into the the
public conversation and
mind there's there's too much certainty
out there there's certainty with the
blue pill certainty with the red pill
and the the gray pill offers us to speak
in such a way where we can be assertive
with our truths but with a caveat saying
I could be wrong so there's a sense that
I think lots of us share is that debate
is broken people are just talking past
each other it's sort of a dog and pony
show and there's this term by Scott
Aikens and Robert Ellie is that quite
like called the dialectic fallacy where
you're sort of gesturing towards your
interlocutor that you're having a
conversation with them but really you're
just trying to score points to your
tribe so the anti defeat is an idea to
attract people to the debate format but
it's not about winning it's about who
can be better at understanding so it
really is a Trojan horse towards more
authentic dialogues and once you get we
experimented with in Toronto and it's
quite powerful once you get a taste of
that you want more of it and once you
get rid of that adversarial frame you
just sort of lose the structure and then
you just want to have a free associate
of exploratory conversation so this is
term that I quite like called the
meta-crisis how I currently hold it is
that there's a lot of existential risks
out there from economic environment AGI
that threaten our existence and with all
these existential risks is coupled with
this inability to sense make an ability
to have conversations to figure out what
to do about it and all the crisis is
that we mentioned sort of baked in this
this meta crisis and my sense and I
think John Vicki would agree with me is
that the first domino to knock over to
address all the other crises is the
meaning crisis and there's a sense
amongst the sense makers in the sense
making a web is that meeting in person
and engaging in these authentic
dialogues whether it's circling
restorative circles incite dialogue you
get in person and do these things and
create a more
body tried rather than just a memetic
tribe could be the answer so I could be
wrong but my sense is that we need to be
more comfortable with the state of
uncertainty and the intellectual
Explorers Club here in Toronto is an
opportunity for that it's an opportunity
to be a performative agnostic to sort of
explore different ideas that are
radically foreign to you and once were
uncomfortable with this state once we we
add nuance to our ideas when we become
grey pilled then I think we can start
practicing these conversational
modalities is these authentic
conversations that invite us to explore
areas or we don't know where we're going
and I think that is needed in order to
address the situation we're in
well done for making it to the end just
wanted to let you know a few things
we've got coming up including the
biggest event we've ever done the rebel
wisdom festival which will be a mix of
ideas and dialogues between people like
Daniel Shmack Tim burger Bonita Roy
Rupert Sheldrake Jamba Vicki and many
more and because wisdom isn't just
intellectual it's also about practice
will be offering experiences like
circling different interpersonal
dialogue mindfulness breathwork and many
other with world-class facilitators and
if you're enjoying the content you can
help us make more by joining the rebel
wisdom club which will give you
discounts and the courses and the events
and also access to a load more content
on the website including all of our live
events it'll also give you access to our
growing community which is something we
want to make a real focus for 2020
adding more meetups and other services
for members so I hope you enjoyed the
film and see you soon
you